# 今天做一个四川农家的菜
Today we are making a Sichuan dish
# 这叫东坡豆花
called Dongpo tofu
# 麻婆豆腐多费劲啊
Mapo tofu needs too much effort
# 这烧出来比麻婆豆腐还好吃
and this dish tastes even better than that
# 真的
Honestly
# 这个其实在大概在七八年前
Actually about 7,8 years ago,
# 或者十年左右
or 10 years ago,
# 在北京的大大小小的川菜馆 都有的卖
this dish could be found in any Sichuan restaurant in Beijing
# 然后我们今天就让大家
Today we will teach you guys
# 真正知道东坡豆花
how to cook Dongpo tofu at home
# 我们自己家庭里面怎么去实现它
# 好不好 好 开始
Ok? Let's start
# 肉 姜 蒜 小香葱 花生碎
Meat, ginger, garlic, spring onions and chopped peanuts
# 我今天是用的内酯豆腐
I'm using silken tofu today
# 又好吃又嫩 简单些
It is delicious and soft
# 炒臊子也比较简单
It is also very easy to make the topping
# 杨兵 我有一次到四川
Yang Bing, I was in Sichuan once
# 到四川都江堰的码头上
We were on the dock at Dujiangyan
# 看见一个大姐 说幺妹儿 卖啥子嘞
and saw a lady and asked "Hey sister, what are you selling?"
# 卖豆花嘞
"I'm selling tofu!"
# 我说幺妹儿来一碗
So I got a bowl
# 多少钱嘞 八块钱
“How much?” “8 kuai!”
# 然后盛了一碗
And she gave me a bowl
# 我吃得非常安逸
I enjoyed it so much
# 那个汁那个味道 巴巴适适嘞
The taste of the sauce was so delicious
# 在四川
In Sichuan,
# 豆花挑起卖 鸡肉挑起卖
Tofu is sold in pails, so is chicken,
# 冰粉挑起卖 凉面挑起卖
Bingfen and cold noodles
# 美食在民间
Real delicacy is in the streets
# 越是挑起担子这个味道 巴巴适适嘞
The food sold in the pails tastes the best
# 好了 一定要热锅凉油
Ok, make sure your wok is hot and the oil is cold
# 你看你们俩谁是四川人
Time to see who is the real Sichuanese
# 我怎么觉得他倒像四川人 我不太像
I feel like he's the real Sichuanese and I'm not
# 杨兵倒不像四川人 你倒像四川人
Yangbing is not a Sichuanese, you are!
# 先得把这个 用的是五花肉
Let's cook the meat first.
# 五花肉肥瘦的
We are using pork belly.
# 如果太瘦了就干巴了 发柴
If the meat is too lean, it will be too dry once cooked
# 炒酥了 又酥又香
Cook it till crispy and fragrant
# 一定要炒出那个香味
Make sure to cook until fragrant
# 你看水汽没有了
Look, now there is no more water
# 放一个川菜之魂
Time for the soul of Sichuan food
# 郫县豆瓣酱
Pixian doubanjiang
# 给一个差不多合适的量
Put in the amount you want
# 豆瓣酱盐度基本上是百分之二十
There's 20% salt in doubanjiang
# 所以菜不再放盐了
So you don't need to put in extra salt
# 豆瓣酱出香味 必须得出
Also make sure to cook the doubanjiang until fragrant
# 其实这个关键点就在于这个
There are two key points
# 豆瓣酱要炒香 肉的水分要炒干
One is to cook the doubanjiang fragrant and the other is to cook the liquid out of the meat
# 那个味道才会出来 香味来了
That's where the flavour comes from
# 这时候放点 姜末可以多一点
Now we can put in some minced ginger
# 姜蒜末一定要新鲜
Make sure to use fresh minced ginger and garlic
# 做的时候吃的时候再放
Put it in when you are cooking
# 这个时候放点豌豆（煮熟的）
We can put in some blanched peas
# 我这个不放豆豉
I'm not putting in any "Douchi" fermented soybeans
# 因为整个都是姜蒜末和豆瓣酱
So the dish is full of the fragrance from
# 还有肉末的香味
ginger, garlic, doubanjiang and meat
# 这边我稍微放一点水
Adding in a bit of water
# 他就不放（豆豉）
He's stubborn about not putting in Douchi
# 让它先咕嘟一下 准备放调料
Let it bubble for a bit, and I will prepare the seasoning
# 酱油 先把颜色调一调
Some soy sauce for the color
# 这黄酒要烹一下
Steam the huangjiu a bit
# 直接放进去
If you just put it in directly
# 肯定是味道出不来那个感觉
You would miss the aroma from huangjiu
# 烹一下
Cook it a bit
# 小火 这就小火不要太大
Keep it on low heat
# 太大水分就收干了
If the heat is too high, it will be too dry
# 放一点点的味精鸡精
A bit of MSG
# 放一点胡椒粉
A bit of black pepper powder
# 其实也可以根据个人口味不放味精
If you don't like MSG, leave it out
# 来一点点的芡粉 不用太多
A bit of slurry, you don't need too much
# 千万不要收的太干了
Don't cook it until too dry
# 很简单这个菜
This is a very simple dish
# 可以再来一点点老抽
A bit of dark soy sauce
# 这个肉是白的
The meat looks a bit too light
# 安逸
Nice
# 这个菜虽说简单
Even though this dish is simple
# 但是它有根 它有四川的根
But it has it's Sichuan roots
# 砂锅 让它有点温度
Let's warm up the clay pot
# 我在这里要放点盐 烧火
I'm putting some salt here - Turn on the heat
# 待会儿才有那个感觉
Wait for the presentation of this dish
# 这回知道内脂豆腐拿回去怎么吃了吧
Now you know how to cook silken tofu now
# 温度起来了 安逸
It is heating up, nice!
# 放在这上面
Putting it here
# 你看一弄这红油 这个透亮
Look at the red oil, how glossy it is
# 这菜我跟你说网友绝对喜欢
I guarantee you our followers will love this dish
# 家里面就自己做了 回家能做
This is very reproducible at home
# 吃个主食吃个米饭 那叫一个香的
You can pair this with rice, so yummy
# 撒点花生碎 撒点葱花
Some chopped peanuts and scallion
# 还有一个很好玩的 把高度的白酒
One more trick, here is some high alcohol content baijiu
# 就瞬间你赶紧照 点着它
And you can light it up right away
# 这个菜就完成了
That's the dish
# 先给师父先给师父
Let your master taste it first
# 师父嘴急先给师父
Your master is very excited to try
# 我好为难哦
You are putting me in a difficult position
# 来点臊子 没有臊子不巴适
A bit more topping, it is not delicious without the topping
# 这菜做得好
Such a nice dish
# 味道香 味道浓 香辣适口
Fragrant, lots of flavours and not too spicy
# 咸鲜辣 然后酥
Savory, umami, spicy and crispy
# 肉末的酥 豆腐的嫩
The crispiness from the meat mince, the softness of the tofu
# 还有葱花的提出的香味
And the scallion brings out extra fragrance
# 然后还有鲜
and umami
# 麻婆豆腐多费劲啊
Mapo tofu takes so much more effort than this
# 这烧出来比麻婆豆腐还好吃
But this tastes so much better than Mapo tofu
# 网友毛肚是柯基问
So your follower wants to
# 想问大爷二伯
ask Daye and Erbai
# 鱼香汁怎么调才好吃
How to make yuxiang sauce
# 糖醋等调味品的比例
What's the ratio between sugar,
# 大概是多少
vinegar and other seasonings
# 二伯
Erbai
# 就是碗芡
This is just a bowl of slurry
# 这里边有酱油
With soy sauce
# 有料酒
Liaojiu,
# 是吧
# 有糖和醋
sugar and vinegar
# 盐
salt
# 过去还有味精胡椒粉
We used to put in MSG and black pepper powder
# 其实就是糖和醋的比例
But the key is the ratio of sugar and vinegar
# 您做鱼香汁
How do you decide the ratio
# 它糖醋的比例是怎么定的
of sugar and vinegar
# 基本都是1:1的事
Usually I just keep it 1:1
# 比如说一两糖
If you use 1 liang (500g) sugar
# 基本就是一两醋
you need 1 liang (500g) vinegar
# 是吧
# 再少也不能少过八钱去
You can't use less than 8 qian (40g)
# 它就这个比例拿捏好了
As long as you can take control of the ratio
# 这糖和醋的比例
The ratio of sugar and vinegar
# 这个菜基本就成功了
This will be a successful dish
# 碗芡里边
In the seasoned slurry
# 你要不搁葱姜蒜
If you don't put scallion, ginger and garlic
# 那个味道就激发不出来
The flavour would be missing
# 还得把这个碗芡里边这味道呢
You have to combine the flavours in the seasoned slurry
# 跟那葱姜蒜也得泡进去
With scallion, ginger and garlic
# 它两方面使
You should put it in twice
# 这两次都是什么时候搁
When do you usually add it?
# 一个是煸锅的时候放
First when the wok is just hot
# 一个是在碗芡里边放上葱姜蒜
The other is when you add the scallion, ginger and garlic
# 那样的这味道一下就激发出来
To bring out the flavour
# 好的
Ok
# 大爷那您做鱼香汁有什么技巧吗
Daye, do you have any advice for Yuxiang sauce?
# 刚才二伯说的挺多的啊
Erbai has said quite a bit
# 我稍微补充一点
I will add one thing
# 关键是炒汁
The key is about cooking the sauce
# 我们准备一份葱姜蒜
Prepare some scallion, ginger and garlic
# 蒜的比例稍微大一点
More garlic than the other two
# 基本上比如说
For example,
# 搁上10克的葱
10g of scallions
# 5克的姜
5g of ginger
# 蒜也得10克
10g of garlic
# 要多一点
or more
# 多一点的时候
When you have more garlic
# 搁一半在锅底
Leave half at the bottom of the wok
# 先煸葱姜蒜
Cook the scallion, ginger and garlic first
# 然后煸郫县豆瓣酱和泡椒
Then add doubanjiang and pickled chili
# 混在一起的
Mix it together
# 煸出红油来
Cook until the red oil comes out of the doubanjiang
# 这时候我们把滑好的肉丝
Then we can put in
# 可以下锅了
the already pan fried meat slices
# 刚才二位讲的这个
Erbai just mentioned
# 叫兑一碗芡
the bowl of seasoned slurry
# 这个碗芡很重要
This is a very important bowl
# 里边要有一点酱油
There should be some soy sauce
# 基本上是
Usually
# 比如说搁5克或者10克的酱油
5 or 10g of soy sauce
# 要搁1:1的醋和糖
Vinegar and sugar with a ratio of 1:1
# 比如还要搁一点点味精
A bit of MSG if you want
# 然后这个碗芡呢
Put the other half of scallion
# 再把另一半的葱姜蒜
Ginger and garlic in the
# 放到这碗堑里头
seasoned slurry
# 用那个碗芡汁
Using the seasoned slurry
# 把葱姜蒜的味道
To bring out the flavour
# 给它释放出来
Of scallion, ginger and garlic
# 然后加上淀粉
And then you can add starch
# 等肉丝下锅以后
Once the sliced meat is in the wok
# 什么笋丝啊木耳啊
You can add sliced bamboo shoots
# 下锅了
Or wood ear mushroom
# 进行翻炒以后
Toss and cook everything
# 一看肉丝红亮
When the meat is red and bright
# 都是郫县豆瓣酱和泡椒的颜色
From the color of doubanjiang and pickled chili
# 这时候把这碗芡往里面一倒
Now we put in the seasoned slurry
# 等了5秒钟左右的时间
After 5 seconds
# 等汁芡
The slurry will become thick
# 那里边有淀粉
There is starch
# 经过加热收缩
Once heated
# 淀粉的粘稠
The starchy water becomes quite thick
# 然后一翻锅
And you toss everything together
# 一翻锅
# 如果说有的掌握不准的时候
If you missed the timing
# 可能这一翻锅
And felt the sauce isn't thick enough
# 感觉这嵌汁稍微差点
When you tossed
# 就收不住
Then add
# 然后再跟着再来点芡
a bit more slurry
# 补芡 补点芡
Patch in more slurry
# 补点芡呢
# 现在醋是一个大问题
The choice of vinegar is also a big issue
# 有的醋呢
Some vinegar
# 他酸味儿不够
is not sour enough
# 有5度的有8度的有11度有13度的
There is 5 degrees, 8 degrees, 11 and 13 degrees
# 但我们感觉醋味一烹啊
But when the vinegar is cooked
# 醋味降低了
It's not as vinegary
# 在出锅之前
So add a bit more vinegar
# 再补充一点醋
Right before serving
# 再一出锅
And the plate it on the dish
# 这个醋就完全在锅里了
Now the vinegar is incorporated with the dish
# 这个味儿特别
The flavor is
# 有点什么呢
A little
# 甜
Sweet
# 酸
Sour
# 辣
Spicy
# 咸
Savory
# 鲜
Umami
# 这么一个味道
Everything combined
# 首先搁嘴里是辣
When you put it in your mouth, the first thing you taste is spicy
# 有点甜
Then sweet
# 然后回口有点儿酸
And the after taste is a bit sour
# 还有点儿鲜
and you can taste the umami flavor
# 这种味道
It is all the flavours combined
# 出来这汁又红又亮
The sauce is bright and red
# 这就是鱼香
This is yuxiang
# 不管是鱼香茄子
You can cook yuxiang eggplant,
# 鱼香虾球
Yuxiang shrimp,
# 鱼香肉片等等
Yuxiang meat slices and may more
# 都可以这样用这碗汁
You can use the same sauce
# 首先我们的网友要把这碗汁
You need to practice and
# 在不断的要去实践好
experiment with the sauce
# 才能做出
Then you can
# 像鱼香这样的口味的菜
cook yuxiang dishes
# 就好吃了没了
And it will be so delicious
# 好谢谢
Thank you!